Finding Aid for C. Theodore Larson papers, 1930-1985
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
C. Theodore Larson papers 1930-1985, 1951-1974
Larson, Carl Theodore, 1903-1988.
(in 5 boxes)
4 linear feet
9438 Aa 2
Professor of architecture at the University of Michigan. The series in the collection are: Architectural Research, 1932-1983; College of Architecture and Urban Planning, 1967-1985; Correspondence, 1962-1972; Development Index, 1947-1984; and Published Materials, 1930-1982.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
These papers (Donor no. 8257 ) were accessioned in May 1995.
The collection is open to research.
Before coming to the University of Michigan in 1948 as professor of architecture, Theodore Larson held the following positions in Washington D.C.: architect and project planner, U.S. Housing Authority, 1939-1940; representative for District of Columbia locality, administrator's office, National Housing Agency, 1942-1944; technical consultant (Housing and Science Legislation), Senate Military Affairs Committee, Subcommittee on War Mobilization, 1944-1945; and assistant technical director, National Housing Agency, 1946.
Professor Larson was associate editor of Architectural Record from 1930 to 1936; research consultant of the F. W. Dodge Corporation from 1937 to 1939; technical editor of the Architectural Forum from 1941 to 1942; technical director of General Homes, Inc., 1947; and associate editor of Architectural Forum in 1948.
He was a member of the Committee on Research for Architecture, American Institute of Architects; the Building Research Advisory Board, NAS-NAE-NRC; Chairman of the Committee on Research and Graduate Studies, Association of Collegiate Schools of Architecture; and was made a Fellow of the American Institute of Architects in May, 1967, "for achievements in education."
Professor Larson was also involved with development of the specialized flows of information needed for coordinated planning of the built environment worldwide. He was the co-author, along with K. Lonberg-Holm of several influential publications including Planning for Productivity, Development Index, and Role of the Mass Media of Information. The last of these was prepared for European Cultural Foundation's Plan Europe and was published in 1972 by Martinus Nijhoff as one of the 17 prospective studies in The Future is Tomorrow.
In addition to all his numerous accomplishments Professor Larson still found time to conceive and initiate the Architectural Research Laboratory (ARL) on the campus of the University of Michigan in 1948. This was the first university architectural lab of its kind anywhere. He remained the director of the lab until 1973. Professor Larson was on the faculty of the University of Michigan's College of Architecture and Urban Planning from 1948 to 1973. He continued as a professor emeritus from 1973 to 1988. He had two sons Dana and Ronal and is also survived by his widow Myra Larson. She also taught at the University of Michigan, within the School of Art.
The papers of C. Theodore Larson measure 4.0 linear feet and date from 1930 to 1985. The bulk of materials, however, are from 1951 to 1974. The papers contain five series: Architectural Research; College of Architecture and Urban Planning; Correspondence; Development index and Published materials.
Subjects:
Architects--Michigan.; Architecture--Michigan.; Buildings, Prefabricated--Michigan.; Larson, Carl Theodore, 1903-; Unistrut Corporation (Wayne, Mich.); University of Michigan. College of Architecture and Design.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Architecture--Research.; University of Michigan. Architectural Research Laboratory.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Buildings, Prefabricated.; Dwellings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Buildings, Prefabricated--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Unistrut Corporation (Wayne, Mich.); University of Michigan. Architectural Research Laboratory.
Contributors:
Lönberg-Holm, Knud, 1895-
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Architectural Research
  The Architectural Research series (2.0 linear foot, 1932-1983) includes three areas of research. The first area encompasses the University of Michigan's Architectural Research Lab which was begun by C. Theodore Larson. This segment contains general information and a portion of the specific projects conducted at the lab. The second area of the series features architectural research that was not conducted at the University of Michigan. It also includes the influential Larson and Lonberg-Holm publication Planning for Productivity. The third area documents environmental and related research. This area records the effect architecture has on the environment. These environmental concerns include both the natural and built environment.
  - University of Michigan Architectural Research Lab
    - Comparison and Evaluation of Polyurethane Foam Shell Roof System by Means of the Time Sharing Computer System in Basic 1966 (Box 1)
    - General Information 1962-1977 (Box 1)
    - HUD-Supported Work-Study Projects for Minorities in Planning and Related Professions 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - Research on Potential of Advanced Technology for Housing 1968 (Box 1)
    - Study of Facilities for Infant Care and Training
      - 1968 (Box 1)
      - 1969 (Box 1)
    - The Effect of Windowless Classrooms on Small School Children 1965 (Box 1)
    - Structural Potential of Foam Plastics for Housing in Underdeveloped Areas 1965 (Box 1)
    - Uni-Strut School Construction 1951 (Box 1)
    - Uni-Strut System of Construction 1956 (Box 1)
      (includes photographs)
  - General Research
    - Architectural Psychology 1972 (Box 1)
    - Building and Housing Research 1953 (Box 1)
    - Building Industry 1935 (Box 1)
      Dutch Language Article
    - Catalog Design Standards 1936 (Box 1)
    - Classification for Building Documentation 1953 (Box 1)
    - Design Training for the Building Industry 1942 (Box 1)
    - "Detroit Housing" 1940s (Box 1)
    - Developing an Integrated System of Education for the Building Industry 1966 (Box 1)
    - Development Problems with Component Construction 1961 (Box 1)
    - "The Emerging Superindustry of Building" 1968 (Box 1)
    - "Expert Says Buildings Should Be Changeable" 1959 (Box 1)
    - Futures Research
      - 1970-1972 (Box 1)
      - 1972-1974 (Box 1)
    - House Construction 1935 (Box 1)
    - "Industrialization of Housing" 1938 (Box 1)
    - "Market Hall of Reinforced Concrete, Vevey, Switzerland 1936 (Box 1)
    - Modular Coordination and School and Design 1967 (Box 1)
    - Modular Coordination 1960 (Box 1)
    - More for Less in Housing 1937 (Box 1)
    - Notes on Consumer Cooperation 1936 (Box 1)
    - "Packaged Houses" 1937 (Box 1)
    - Performance Concept 1965-1966 (Box 1)
    - Performance of Buildings 1961 (Box 1)
    - Planning for Productivity 1940 (Box 1)
    - "Political Aspects of City Planning and Housing" 1934 (Box 1)
    - Progressive Architecture-Improved Materials 1954 (Box 2)
    - Questionnaires for Catalog Information 1938 (Box 2)
    - Recent Developments in Building Classification 1959 (Box 2)
    - The Regional Housing Centre, Bandung, Indonesia 1958 Planning for Productivity, 1940 (Box 2)
    - Research In Architecture 1965 (Box 2)
    - Self Help Housing Construction: The State of the Art in Terms of Technical Innovation 1972 (Box 2)
  - "Special Report-Architectural Forum," The Magazine of Building, 1955
    - A Survey of the International Building Classification Committee 1952-1962 (Box 2)
    - A Systems Approach to the Performance Concept in Building 1966 (Box 2)
    - "Time Zoning as a Preventive for Blighted Areas" 1933 (Box 2)
    - Trends in Building Production 1936 (Box 2)
    - "Toward a Science of Housing" 1947 (Box 2)
    - Uni-Strut Space Frame 1965 (Box 2)
    - "The U.S. Building: Case Problem in Communications" 1952 (Box 2)
  - Environmental Research
    - Aesthetics of 20th Century Architecture 1948 (Box 2)
    - The Age of Astro-Architecture 1983 (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor Environmental Interpretive Center 1964-1968 (Box 2)
    - "Buckminister Fuller-Futurist Ideas" 1981 (Box 2)
    - "The Changing Urban Patterns of a Global Society" 1980 (Box 2)
    - Chinese Center/Child Development 1982 (Box 2)
    - Cities 1959-1970 (Box 2)
    - "Community Development" 1936-1981 (Box 2)
    - Contrary to the Sound of Battelle 1968 (Box 2)
    - "Design for Environmental Control" 1936 (Box 2)
    - "Dialing for Weather" 1934 (Box 2)
    - "Downsizing at the University of Michigan" 1982-1983 (Box 2)
    - Environmental Analysis 1970 (Box 2)
    - Environmental Design and Research 1969 (Box 2)
    - Future Shock Hits the American Courthouse 1975 (Box 2)
    - Huron Valley Inter-Urban Growth Analysis 1978 (Box 2)
    - Integration In Design as a Factor in Conflict Resolution 1950s (Box 2)
    - Limits to Growth 1972 (Box 2)
    - MacArthur Foundation 1972 (Box 2)
    - New Schools for New Education 1959 (Box 2)
    - Nuclear/Technology 1982 (Box 2)
    - A Pattern Language Which Generates Multi-Service Centers 1968 (Box 2)
    - Socio-Physical Environment 1967 (Box 2)
    - Shelter Magazine 1932 (Box 2)
    - Social Environment, National Values Project 1932 (Box 2)
    - "Some European Nursery Schools and Playgrounds" 1970 (Box 2)
    - Urban Design 1982 (Box 2)
    - Unified Transportation Systems and Future Urban and Regional Development 1969 (Box 2)
- College of Architecture and Urban Planning
  The series designated College of Architecture and Urban Planning (0.1 linear foot, 1967-1985) documents developments of the College of Architecture and Urban Planning. These events include the effect of computers on architectural education and the school's new building on North Campus.
  - Computer Aided Material Selection for Building Enclosure Systems (Box 3)
  - The Computer and Architectural Education 1967 (Box 3)
  - Planning a Professional Goldfish Bowl 1985 (Box 3)
- Correspondence
  Correspondence (0.1 linear foot, 1962-1972) is a series that is composed of written communication between Theodore Larson and his main collaborator, K. Lonberg-Holm. Many different ideas and concepts are covered in this correspondence, including research ideas such as the "windowless classroom", exchange of contemporary articles that related to their areas of interest, revisions of their publications, and actual sketches of ideas.
  - K. Lonberg-Holm
    - 1962-1967 (Box 3)
    - 1968-1972 (Box 3)
- Development Index
  The Development Index (0.5 linear foot, 1947-1984) is a series built around one of Theodore Larson's greatest achievements. This achievement is the conception and writing (along with his collaborator K. Lonberg-Holm) of the Development Index. The Development Index is a "proposed pattern for organizing and facilitating the flow of information needed by man in furthering his own development, with particular reference to the development of buildings and communities and other forms of environmental control." Information that is related to the index is also included.
  - Computer Information Structures 1974 (Box 3)
  - Concept of Development 1971-1982 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 1953 (Box 3)
  - Designing Information 1947 (Box 3)
  - Development Index 1953 (Box 3)
  - Global Concepts 1961-1979 (Box 3)
  - Hierarchy of Needs 1984 (Box 3)
  - A Holistic Approach for Integrating Information Science Research 1979 (Box 3)
  - Human Systems Management 1972 (Box 3)
  - Information Systems 1973-1979 (Box 3)
  - Information Theory 1954 (Box 3)
  - International Development 1974 (Box 3)
  - Long Term Alternatives Suggested by Information Technology 1980 (Box 3)
  - The Problem of Defining Information Science 1979 (Box 3)
  - "Role of Mass Media on Information and Communication" 1972 (Box 3)
  - Shaping the Future of a Global Society and Achieving Wisdom 1979 (Box 3)
  - "There's a Systems Ideology In your Future" 1974 (Box 3)
- Published Materials
  Published Materials (1.0 linear foot, 1930-1982) is a series of publications which Theodore Larson has either written, has edited or done both. The last two works were done by associates. Publications include The Architectural Forum, The Architectural Record, HSM (Human Systems Management), Catalog Design Progress, and Structural Analysis of "Uni-Strut" Space-Frame Roofs.
  - The Architectural Forum, 1942, 2 issues (Box 4)
  - The Architectural Forum, 1942, 2 issues (Box 5)
    (continued)
  - The Architectural Record, 1930-1938, 16 issues (Box 4)
  - The Architectural Record, 1930-1938, 16 issues (Box 5)
  - HSM (Human Systems Management), 1982, 1 volumes (Box 4)
  - HSM (Human Systems Management), 1982, 1 volumes (Box 5)
  - Catalog Design Progress, 1950 (Box 4)
  - Catalog Design Progress, 1950 (Box 5)
  - Structural Analysis of "Uni-Strut" Space-Frame Roofs (a&b), 1959 (Box 4)
  - Structural Analysis of "Uni-Strut" Space-Frame Roofs (a&b), 1959 (Box 5)